<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno regni Regis Henrici VIII quinto statuta ...</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1515</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9362.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22363665</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22363665</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1752:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno regni Regis Henrici VIII quinto statuta ...</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : coat of arms.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Pynson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1515]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Publisher and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:25461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25461:1"/>
            <head>Anno regni Regis Henrici .viii. Quinto.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>tatuta</head>
            <p>¶ The kynge our ſouerreyne lorde Henry the .viii. after the conqueſt by the grace of god kyng of Englande and of Fraunce / and lorde of Irlande / at his Patlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at weſtmeſter / the .xxiii. daye of Ianuarii after the laſt Porrogacion. In the .v. yere of his moſt noble Reygne to the honoure of god &amp; holy Churche / and for the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth &amp; profyte of this his Royalme / by the aſſente of the Lordes
<abbr>ſpirituall</abbr> &amp; <abbr>temporall:</abbr> &amp; the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent Parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled: and by auctoryte of the ſame hath do to be ordeyned made and enacted certayne Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes / and ordynaunces in maner &amp; fourme folowynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:25461:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>Hec roſa virtutis de celo miſſa ſereno. Eternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> florens regia ſceptra feret.</q>
                  <figDesc>royal English blazon or coat of arms with Tudor rose, supported by angels,a dragon and a dog, between two portcullises</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:25461:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Anno regni Regis Henrici .viii. Quinto.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>An act concernynge Mynyſtracyon of Iuſtyce to the kynges ſubiectis of his Cytie of Turney.</head>
               <head type="sub">Capitulo. Primo</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as the Kynge oure Soueraygne Lorde gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly deſirynge to recouere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realme of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his very trewe Patrymonye and inherytaunce &amp; to reduce the ſame to his obey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunce. And for the ſame purpoſe and ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lately made Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of great Royall Armyes aſ well by ſee as by lande to his right great and merueylous coſtes and charge / And ſythen that by his great wiſdome and ſinguler polyce hath now reduced the Cities and tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of Tyrrewyn / and Turney to dewe obeyſaunce by reaſon wherof nowe ſhall folowe &amp; enſue great Amyte Famylyarite &amp; entercours in byeng &amp; ſellyng of mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſes wares &amp; otherwyſe bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cyteze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; inhabytau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd cyties Townes and Precinctꝭ of the ſame / and the kynges Naturall ſubiectis inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunces in this hys Realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / Therfore the kynge our ſouereygne lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wyllynge and entendynge that trewe &amp; indyfferent Iuſtyce ſhalbe mynyſtred in al maters and cauſes aſwell to Cytezens and inhabytauntes dwellynge and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>habytynge in the ſame Cyties / Townes / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precinctꝭ of the ſame / As to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſubiectis dwellynge within this his Realme of Englande / And to the ſame en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent the kynge our ſouereygne Lorde hath deputed and ordeyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Cytie and towne of turney and in the Bayllywyke and precincte of the ſame dyuerſe of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycers and Mynyſters / &amp; amonge other two of them called Notaryes otherwyſe called Graffers to accepte take and recorde the knolege of all contractes bargay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes conuencyons pactis and agrementes made and to be made within the ſayde Cytie and towne of Turney bayllywyke and precincte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by all maner of ꝑſones that wyll and ſhall reſorte and come before them to make knowlege of the ſame / whiche Notaryes or Graffers ſhall preſent and deliuer in wrytyng all ſuche knolege as ſhalbe ſo taken vnder theyr Notarye ſygnes vnto an other offycer of the ſame Cytie and towne / whiche our ſayd ſoueraygne Lorde hathe there made and deputed to accepte and take of them the ſame whiche offycer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more affyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof ſhall ſette therto the Seale of our ſouereygne lorde made and lefte in the kepynge of the ſame Offycer for the ſame ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. The kynge our ſoueragne Lorde by thaſſent of his lordes <abbr>Spu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all</abbr> &amp;
<abbr>temporall</abbr> / and the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlyament aſſembled and by Auctoryte of the ſame hath ordeyned and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that vpon euery wrytynge oblygatorie &amp; knowlege to be made of all contractꝭ bargaynes conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions pactꝭ and agrementꝭ / ſygned and Sealed in forme aboue reherſed / by any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges ſubiectes inhabyted in this Realme of Englande to any Cytezen or inhabytaunte within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Cytie and towne of Turney Baylly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyke or precyncte of the ſame or by any Cytezen or inhabytaunt within the ſame Cytye / Towne / Bayllywyke or precincte to an other of the ſame or ells by any cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tezen or inhabytaunte of the ſame Cytie
/ Towne Bayllywyke or precincte to any <pb facs="tcp:25461:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the kyngꝭ ſubiectꝭ Inhabyted within the Realme of Englande / or by any of the kynges ſubiectes inhabyted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realme of Englande / to another of the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectis ſhewed and exhybyted to the Chaunceller of Englande / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme beynge the ſame Chaunceller haue full auctoryte and powre vpon the ſyght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a Sargeaunte of Armes or another offycer to the ꝑſone ſo bounden to requy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the parſone ſo bounden to ꝑfourms the contentes of euery ſuche wrytynge oblygatorye and knowlege / and if the ſame ꝑſones ſo bounden denye ſo to do and obiecte or alege any cauſe why he ſhulde not ſo doo / then the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or offycer immedyatly ſhall brynge the ſame parſone ſo bounden before the Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celler of Englande to anſwere to the premyſſes. And if the ꝑſon ſo bounden and brought before the ſayd Chaunceller obiecte or alege any mater or cauſe reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable why he ſhulde not ꝑfourme the Contentꝭ of the ſame wrytynge oblygatorye and knowlege that then he ſhalbe adiuged to brynge in ſuffycyent Gage &amp; plegge to the verye value of the contentes of the ſame wrytynge obligatorye into the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges Courte of Chauncerye or ellys to remayne in warde / And then the ſayd Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celler by his wyſdome and diſcrecion ſhall prefixe and aſſigne vnto hym a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyent ꝑemptorie daye to proue his obieccion and aligacion / and if the ꝑtie ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den proue not his obieccion and allegacion before the ſayd Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celler to be trewe before or at the ſayd daye prefixed / that then the ſayd ꝑtie ſo bounden without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay ſhall ꝑfourme the Contentꝭ of the ſayd oblygacyon and knowlege then not per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fourmed or ellys to forfayte the ſayd Gages and plegges to the partie to whom y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayd oblygacyon or knowlege was made / And in lykewyſe vpon all recognyſaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces to be made before the kynge in his Chauncery or in his Benche or in any other the kynges Courte of recorde within the Realme of Englande / And alſo vpon all wrytynges oblygatorye to be made and knoleged before the Mayre of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of calyce of all debtꝭ contractes and bargaynes by any of the ſayd Cytizens or inhabytauntes of the ſayd Cytie or towne of Turney or Baylywyke or precincte of the ſame to any of the kynges ſubiectes / and the ſame knolege or wrytynge ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligatorie be then certified to the Baylyff of the ſame Cytie &amp; Towne by the Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celler of Englande vnder the kyngꝭ great Seale of Englande / that then the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of the ſame Cytie and Towne for the tyme beynge or his deputie haue full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoryte and power to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and ſhall ſende a Sergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or other offycer of the ſame Cytie and Towne to the ꝑſone ſo boundem to requyre and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the ſame ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſo bounden to parfourme the Contentes of the ſame knolege and wrytynge oblygatorye / And if the ꝑtie ſo bounden denye ſo to do and obiecte and alege any cauſe why he ſhulde not ſo doo That then the ſayde Sergeaunt or offycer imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyatly ſhall brynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſone ſo bounden before the Baylye of the ſayde Cytie and Towne for the tyme beynge to anſwere to the premyſſes / And if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parſone ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den &amp; brought before the ſayd Bayllye obiecte and alege any mater or cauſe reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable why he ſhulde not ꝑforme the Contentes of the ſame wrytynge oblygatorie and knolege / that then he ſhalbe adiuged to brynge ſuffycyant gayge and pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very value of the Contentꝭ of the ſame wrytynge oblygatorie or knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge into the Courte before the ſame bayly or his deputie or ellys to remayne in war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / <pb facs="tcp:25461:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>And then the ſayd Baylye or his deputie by his wyſdome and diſcrecyon ſhall prefixe &amp; aſſygne vnto hym a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyent ꝑemtorye daye to proue his obieccion &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legacion and if the ꝑtie ſo bounden proue not his obieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and allegacyon before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Baylye or his deputie to be trewe before or at the ſayd daye prefyxte
/ that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd ꝑtie ſo bounden without delaye ſhall ꝑfourme the contentꝭ of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge oblygatorye and knowlege then not parfourmed or ellys to forfayte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Gayges and plegges to the ꝑtie to whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd oblygacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or knowlege was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / This acte to endure durynge the kynges pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte for trewe makynge of clothes in deuon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called whyte ſtraytes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ca .ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rayen the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons and Inhabytauntꝭ cloth makers and byers of the ſame within the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of Deuonſhyre / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where dyuerſe &amp; many clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes called whyte ſtraytes be and haue be contynually made within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie to the great profyte of the kynges ſubiectes there the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che clothes were wont to be well and ſuffycyently made and bere their brede yerde brode and halfe querter Rawe and .xv. yerdes of lenghte / and that no man in tymes paſte hath vſed to make them / but that the maker therof hath ſette his <abbr>ſpecyall</abbr> marke vpon euery of the ſayd clothes ſo by hym or them made / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euery man may knowe theyr owne clothes from other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes by reaſon of their ſayd ſeuerall markꝭ / So it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now adayes the ſayd clothes be not ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ne bere theyr length and brede accordynge as they ſhuld do ne marked with eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry mannes owne marke
/ Wherof great inconuenyence doth dayly Inſue / and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to then poueryſſhynge and hurtynge aſwell of the kyngꝭ ſubiectꝭ byers and ſellers of the ſame / as marchauntes ſtraungers / Wherfore the premiſſes conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd that hit may be therfore / enacted by the kynge our ſoueraygne Lorde / by the aſſent of the Lordes <abbr>ſpyrituall</abbr> and <abbr>temporall</abbr> and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament aſſembled / &amp; by the auctoryte of the ſame / That from the feſt of Pentheco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte nexte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge no ꝑſone make no ſuche clothes called whyte Straytes to ſelle without that it be whene he is rawe redy to be toked of the brede of a yarde &amp; halfe quarter / and of length .xv. yardes / And that no ꝑſone make no ſuche clothes / but if he ſette his ſpecy all marke vpon eueryche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd clothes ſo by hym or them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / And that no ꝑſone vſe no marke on his clothes ſuche as any other ꝑſone dothe and hath vſed before hym vpon payne of a forfayture of euery of the ſayd clothes the one halfe to the kynge / and the other halfe to hym that ſo ſeaſſyeth the ſayd clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes ſo made or marked co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the fourme and effect afore expreſſyd. And this Acte to endure vnto the next Parlyament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte concernynge whyte wolleyn clothes of .v. markes and vnder may be caryed ouer the ſees vnſhorne.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ca .iii.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25461:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>WHere in this preſent Parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before the firſte prorogacion therof it was ordeyned and enacted / that no wolleyne Clothe aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryce of iiii. markes ſhuld be conuayed ouer the ſee vnrowed / vnbarbed
/ &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhorne vpon certeyne penalties in the ſame Acte expreſſed more at lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / Whiche Acte put in execucyon ſhall not only tourne to the abatementꝭ of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges cuſtomes / but alſo grow to the vtter vndoynge of his ſubiectꝭ cloth makers &amp; marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes conuayers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd clothes / For aſmoche as wolle is ryſen of a ferre gretter pryce than it was at the makynge of the ſayd acte / For where a clothe was then comynally ſolde at .iiii. markꝭ is nowe ſolde for. v markꝭ. And alſo by force of the ſayd acte the marchauntꝭ ſulde be bounde to dreſſe euery whyte cloth aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of .iiii. markꝭ on thyſſyde the ſee after they haue bought them / which whyte clothe ſo dreſſyd when they be brought in to the ꝑties beyonde the ſee and therby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byers of them dyed &amp; put in colours / then they muſt be newly dreſſyd / barbed / ſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren / and rowed / And ſo they ſhalbe therby the laſſe in ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them ſelfe / and the worſe to the ſeale &amp; ſolde for laſſe pryce by .x. or .xii. <abbr>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</abbr> a peas beyonde the ſee then they ſhuld be if they were vndreſſed. ¶ Wherfore be it ordeyned and enacted by ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke auctoryte that euery whyte wolleyn clothe ſolde at .v. markꝭ and vnder may be caryed and conueyed into ꝑties beyonde the ſee there to be ſolde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byers of the ſayd Clothe vnbarbed / vnſhorne / &amp; vnrowed any acte or actꝭ to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary made natwithſtandyng / And ouer this be it ordeyned &amp; enacted by the ſayd auctoryte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any ꝑſon or ꝑſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey or cauſe to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyd into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑties beyond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee any whyte wolleyn Cloth vnrowed / vnbarbed / and vnſhorne aboue the value of .v. markꝭ in other fourme then a fore is ſayd / That then the ꝑſone or ꝑſones ſo of fendynge ſhall forfayte the value of the ſayd Cloth or clothes ſo caryed or conueyed in to the ꝑties beyonde the ſee / The one moyte of the ſame forfayture to be to oure ſayd ſoueraygne lorde the kyng / And the other moyte to euery ꝑſone / whiche woll or ſhall ſewe by byll wrytte Informacion or other wyſe ayenſte any ꝑſone for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in any plee vpon any ſuch acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n be nat admytted to wage his lawe nor any proteccion or eſſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any ſuche defendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be alowed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte for advodynge diſceytes in worſtedes.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ca .iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rayen the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſent Parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled that whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as worſtedes whiche ben truly made ſhorne dyed and calendred as of olde tyme hath ben accuſtomed to be made ſhorne dyed &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendred haue ben one of the goodlyeſt marchaundyſe &amp; gretteſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modytie for this Realme / &amp; not only worne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this Realme / But alſo moche worne and vſed in other Realmes / And ſo it is that now of late dyuerſe ſtraungers beyonde the ſee haue taken vpon them to drye Calendre worſtedes with gommes oyles and preſſes ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a cource pece of worſted nat beyng paſt the value of .xxvi. <abbr>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</abbr> viii.
<abbr>d.</abbr> Is and ſhalbe made by theyr ſayd gommes oyles / &amp; preſſes to ſhewe lyke to the value of .xl. <abbr>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</abbr> or better / And if the ſame worſted ſo dry ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lendred taketh any wete incontynent it wolle ſhowe ſpotte and ſhowe fowle / And euer after contynue ſtylle ſoule and <abbr>wollnat</abbr> endure to the great diſceyte &amp; hurte of
<pb facs="tcp:25461:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the werers therof &amp; loſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite / &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd diſceytꝭ &amp; falſnes the ſayd dry calendryng is ſhurned &amp; abhorred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑties beyonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee / So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ꝑſone do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſhall vſe in thoſe ꝑties any ſuche worſtedes to dry calendre / And alſo now of late the ſayd Straungers called dry calenders arne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men into this Realme &amp; here w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd dry cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dryng of worſted &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great hurt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wel &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte of this Realme a foreſayd / wherfore be it enacted ordeyned &amp; eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the aſſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordꝭ
<abbr>ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all</abbr> &amp; <abbr>temporall</abbr> / &amp; the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled &amp; by auctoryte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ꝑſone ne ꝑſons w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this ſayd Ryal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me hereafter do take vpon hym or theym to dry calendre any worſted within this ſayd Realme vpon payne to forfayte for euery worſted that is ſo dry calendred one .C.
<abbr>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</abbr> And ouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where as the ſayd olde calendryng of worſtedes called wete calen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drynge haue ben vſed well &amp; ſubſtancially in tymes paſte in the Cytie of Norwych &amp; yet is by ꝑſones hauyng conyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / Be it therfore furthermore enacted or deyned &amp; eſtabliſſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auctorite aforeſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ꝑſon ne ꝑſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hereafter do take vpon hym or them to were calendre any worſted / but only ſuche ꝑſons as haue ben bounde apprentyſes to other ꝑſones of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame craft or occupaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of wete cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre of worſtedes by the ſpace of .vii. yeres or be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng in the ſame / &amp; theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; admytted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mayre of the ſayd cytie of Norwyche for the tyme beynge &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two Mayſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd crafte &amp; occupacyon yerly to be choſen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the ſayd cytie of Norwyche / or in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of <abbr>Norff</abbr> of the craft of wete cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dryng vpon payne of euery ſuch ꝑſone or ꝑſons / which hereafter ſhall do the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to forfayte for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry pece ſo cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cꝭ &amp; puruyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cꝭ aforeſayd .C.
<abbr>s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</abbr> The one moyte of which penaltes &amp; forfaytours aboue ſpecyfied &amp; of euery of them to be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng our ſoueraygne lorde / And the other moyte therof to be to the Maiſters of the ſayd occupacyon of wete calendryng / for the tyme beyng / And that it ſhalbe laufull to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maiſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd occupacyon for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme beyng / &amp; their ſucceſſours to ſhewe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one moyte of all ſuch penalties hereafter to be forfayted ayenſt euery ſuch ꝑſone or ꝑſones as hereafter ſhall do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourme &amp; effect of this eſtatute by accio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of dette by wrytte at the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawe or by byll or playnt after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cuſtome of ſuche Cytie / port / or towne / where ſhall happon any ſuche forfayture to be or fall / or by in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formacion in the kyngꝭ Eſchequer / And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no proteccion or eſſoine ne no wagere of lawe for the defꝭ in any ſuch accion playnt or informacion be alloweable before any maner of Iuſtycꝭ / where any ſuche ſute or Informacion ſhalbe vſed for the ſayd for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fayture / And this Acte to endure to the next Parlyament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>An acte cocernynge Iurys in London<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ca. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in this preſent Parlyament holden at Weſtmeſter the
.iiii. day of February in the .iii. yere of the reygne of our ſoueraygne lorde the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and proroged vnto the .iiii. daye of Nouember in the .iiii. yere of the reygne of oure ſoueraygne lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng and adiourned vnto Weſtme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter aforeſayd / for aſmoche as after iſſuis Ioyned in accions and ſuet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menſed taken or dependyng i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngꝭ Courtꝭ before hym ſelfe in his Benche &amp; before his Iuſtycꝭ of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men Benche / And alſo in his Eſchequer at the kynges ſuete or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſute of the ꝑtie tryable in the cytie of London aſwell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑties <pb facs="tcp:25461:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuffered great delaye many tymes for defaute of apparens of the Iuryes enpane<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd to trye the ſayd iſſues / and many tymes for lacke of Iurours not hauynge lan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the yerly value of .xl. <abbr>s.</abbr> It was the ſayd .iiii. daye of Nouember ordeyned and enacted by the auctoryte of this preſent Parlyament / that the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffes of London for the tyme beynge ſhulde haue full auctoryte &amp; power to retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in panelles or Arrayes of all accions and ſuetes then dependynge or that ſhulde depende in any of the ſayd Courtes or Eſchequer ꝑſones beynge cytezens hauyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge goodes to the value of .C. marke or aboue to trye the iſſue Ioyned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery ſuche accion or ſute / And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſones ſo retourned hauynge goodes to the value of .C. marke or aboue ſhuld be ſworne and doo in all ſuche Iuryes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lyke wyſe in euery thynge as other ꝑſones ſhulde do hauynge landes ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yerely value of .xl. <abbr>s.</abbr> ouer all charges / And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sheryffes of the ſayd cytie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme beynge ſhuld retourne vpon the firſte diſtreſſe in euery ſuche accion or ſute vpon euery of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours enpaneled to trye the iſſues therof .xx. <abbr>d.</abbr> And vpon the ſeconde diſtreſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery of the ſame Iurours .xl. <abbr>d.</abbr> And vpon euery diſtreſſe after that vpon euery of the ſame Iurours the double / tyll a full Iury in euery ſuche Accion and ſure ſhuld appere &amp; be ſworne to trye the iſſue Ioyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sheryffes that ſhuld make any retourne vpon ſuche diſtreſſes contrarye to the fourme aforeſayd ſhuld forfayte for euery ſuche defaute
.x. <abbr>li.</abbr> The one halfe therof to be to the kynge / And the other halfe to the ꝑtie that will ſewe therfore / And that the defendauntes in any ſuche accion ſhulde not be admytted to wage his lawe nor proteccion therin for hym alowed whiche eſtatute was oonly made for the good Expedycyon of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyce for to haue quycke apparence of Iurours cyteze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Seynt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graunt with in the ſayd cytie / where all Iuryes were &amp; ben bounden oon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to appere to try the iſſues Ioyned of all thynges tryable in London by ꝓceſſes of Niſiprius out of the ſayd Courtꝭ &amp; in none other place accordynge to theyr Aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent lybertie pryuilege and cuſtome / wherfore for more playne declaration of the ſame good eſtatute be it ordeyned and eſtablyſſhed by the auctorite of this preſent Parlyament that the ſayd Acte be expowned interpretated and taken / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> She<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryffes for the tyme beynge be bounden to Retourne at euery firſt diſtreſſe of Niſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prius to be had at the ſayd ſeynt Marteyns in euery ſuche accion or ſute vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Iurours impanelled to trye the iſſues therof .xx. <abbr>d.</abbr> And vpon the ſeconde diſtreſſe of Niſiprius vpon euery of the ſame Iurours .xl.
<abbr>d.</abbr> And vpon euery di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of Niſiprius after that euery of the ſame Iurours the double / tyll a full Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry in euery ſuche accion and ſute ſhall appere &amp; be ſworne to trye the iſſue Ioyned in the ſame / And that no Sheryffe of the ſayd citye or other / any thynge forfayte by force or colour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd eſtatute for euery retourne to be made / except only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Retournes to be made contrary to the fourme declaracion interpretation &amp; expoſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of this Eſtatute / that is to ſaye / vpon writtes of diſtreſſes before Iuſtyces or Iuſtyce of Niſiprius within the ſayd cytye / And that vpon all other wryttes and proceſſes that be &amp; ſhalbe awarded out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd courtꝭ or eſchequer It ſhalbe lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Sheryffes for the tyme beynge to make their Retournes accordyng to the ordre of the lawe as the Sheryffes of London were wonte to do before the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge of the ſayd Eſtatute without any loſſe or forfayture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25461:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>An acte concernynge Surgeons to be diſcharged of queſtes and other thynges.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ca. vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Heweth-vnto your diſcrete wyſdomes your humble Oratours / The war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and feſſhype of the crafte and Mynyſteri of Surgyons enfraunchy ſed in the Cytie of London / not paſſynge in nombre .xii. ꝑſones / That whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as they and theyr predeceſſours from the tyme that no mynde is to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary aſwell in this noble cytie of London / As i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other Cyties and Boroughes within this Reyalme or ellys wherefor the contynuall ſeruyce &amp; attendaunce that they deyly and nyghtly at all houres and tymes yeue to the kynges lege people / for the releue of the ſame accordynge to theyr ſcyence haue ben exempt and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged from all offycers and beſynes / wherin they ſhuld vſe or bere any maner of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure or wepyn / &amp; with lyke pryuylege haue ben entreated as Harowdes of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes aſwell in Batayles and feldes as other places / there for to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnherneyſed and vnwepenned accordyng to the lawe of Armes becauſe they be ꝑſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer vſed Feattes of warre nor ought to vſe / but oonly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſynes &amp; exercyſe of theyr ſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence to the helpe and comforthe of the kyngꝭ lyege people in the tyme of theyr nede / And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayd cytie of London from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of theyr firſte Incorꝑacion when they haue ben many moo in nombre than they be nowe were neuer called nor char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to be on queſte / watche nor other offyce wherby they ſhulde vſe or occupy any Armour or defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cible gere of warre / where thorugh they ſhuld be vnredy &amp; letted to practyſe theyr Cure of men beynge in ꝑell. Therfore for that they be ſo ſmall nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of the ſayd felyſhyppe of the crafte and Myſtery of Surgyons i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regarde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great multytude of pacyentꝭ that be and dayly chaunce and infortune happeneth and encreaſethe in the foreſayde Cytie of London / And that many of the kynges lyege people ſodenly wounded and hurte for defaute of helpe in tyme to theym to be ſhewed peryſſhe / And ſo dyuers haue done as euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cly is knowen by occaſyon that your ſayd Supplyauntes haue ben compelled to attende vpon ſhuche Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bleſhyp / watches and Iuryes as a foreſayd. ¶ Be it enacted &amp; eſtablyſſhed by the kynge our Soueraygne lorde and the lordes <abbr>ſpirituall</abbr> and <abbr>temporall</abbr> / and by the Commons in this preſent Parlyament aſſembled &amp; by actoryte of the ſame / That from henſforth your ſayd ſupplyauntes be diſcharged and not chargeable of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtablyſhyppe / watche and all maner of offyce berynge and Armour / And alſo of all Enqueſtes and Iuryes within the cytie of London / And alſo that this Acte in all thynge do extende to all Barboures Surgyons admytted and aproued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe the ſayd myſterye of Surgyons acccordynge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute late<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly made in that behalfe / So that they excede ne be at one tyme aboue the nombre of .xii. parſones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25461:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>An acte for Strangers for byeng of Lether in open market.</head>
               <head type="sub">Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the moſte humble wyſe ſhewen and complayneth vnto your hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes your pore and dayly Oratoures the Felyſhyppe and broderhed of the bleſſed Trinite at the blacke Fryers in your Cytie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the crafte of Cordewayners ſtraungers / that where at your laſte Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde yere of your moſt noble Reygne amongꝭ other thynges it was accordyd and enacted by an Acte made &amp; graunted vnto the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and felyſhyppe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coriours to haue ſerche of Ledder for certayne cauſes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayde Acte largely named &amp; expreſſed / That no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger Alyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not borne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Realme of Englande / Irlande / Wales / Calyce / or the marcheſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame dwellynge within any Frauncheſed place or places within the precincte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Cytie of London and ſuburbes as in the Frauncheſe of ſeynt Katheryns / ſaynt Martyns in the Towne of Weſtmeſter / and in the borouhe of Southwerke ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de bye or cauſe to be bought to his or to their vſe any ledder or wares in any ſecrete place / but oonly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> market where it ſhulde be ſeen aſſayled ſealed abled good and ſuffycyently tanned &amp; coryed / And alſo that the wardens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coryours their ſucceſſours &amp; aſſygnes ſhuld haue ſerche in the crafte and broderhed of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te aforeſayde aſwell in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chyſed places as in any other place for all maner of ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ledder or ware in ſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly Tanned ſealed and coryed as often as they ſhuld thynke conuenyent / And the ſame ledder ſo founde inſuffycyent to be forfeyted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other paynes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the content of the ſayd Acte lemytte &amp; expreſſed ſythe the makynge of whiche ſtatute many &amp; the moſte ꝑtye of all your ſayd poore oratoures be falle i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great decaye ad pouertie by the meanes of whiche ſtatute the ſayd crafte of Cory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours wrongfully dayly compelle your ſayd pore Oratours ſtraungers borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the domynyon of themperour / and the prince of Caſtell to by their ledder and wares of them and of no ꝑſone ellys after theyr owne pryce without any ryght or conſcience In aſmoche that be force of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue named Acte youre poore oratours ſtraungers may bye no redde ledder as they were wonte to do before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makynge of the ſayde ſtatute / but it muſte be coryed / And ſo if the ſayd ledder be vnlaufully dreſt or coryed all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault retourne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſayd pore oratours / where as a fore tyme they bought bothe redde ledder and other and ſawe that it ſhuld be ſuffyciently co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed and dreſt orells to be forfeyted / Wherefore your ſayd Oratours may not ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſe and ſerue your lordes ſtates &amp; comynaltie / of this your Realme as they were wonte to doo in tymes paſte afore the makynge of the ſayde Acte for as it is open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knowen the ſayd warden and crafte of Coryours dayly ſell the beſte Ledder in groſſe to marchauntes ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers Italyans and other ꝑſones / ſo that your poore oratours be compelled to take and bye of them vnlaufull ledder in retale or elleys in groſſe with ouerchargeable pryce for lacke of a dewe ordre and prouyſion inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyderacion wherof and for the moſt conforte and relefe of the ſayd broderhed and felyſhype of the bleſſyd Trynyte / It woll pleaſe your ſayd hygnes and the lordes <abbr>Spirituall</abbr> and temporalles / and the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this your preſent Parlyament <pb facs="tcp:25461:6"/>aſſembled that it may be therfore ordeyned enacted and eſtablyſſhed / by auctoryte of the ſame that from henſforth it be laufull to all maner of ꝑſone or ꝑſones eſtran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers beynge in the felyſſhyppe of the bleſſed Trinite a foure named &amp; to all maner other ꝑſones borne vnder the domynyon of the Emperour and the prynce of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell to by all maner of redde ledder or other ledder coryed or not coryed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> open mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket and Fayres within this your Realme of englande ſuffycyently wrought aſſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and ſealed with all laufull ſerche in all places Fraunchyſed or Vnfraunchyſed as they haue done and occupyed in tymes paſte afore The makynge of the aboue ſayd Acte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde yere of your reygne without any lette interrupcion and trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble by any ꝑſone or ꝑſones accordynge to the olde vſaunce and cuſtome / The ſayd Acte of coryours ſtatute and ordynaunce or any other acte or actꝭ grauntꝭ ſtatutes or ordynaunces to the contrary made or to be made notwithſtandynge.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alway that this preſent acte do not extende to any other parſone but ſuche as be of the ſayd brotherhed / and to all other ꝑſones borne vnder the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the kynge of caſtell domynyon.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alſo that this acte ſhall not extende to gyue any ꝑſone borne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges obeyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce lybertie to bye any ledder vntanned nor vnſuffycie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly tanned.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded furthermore that no ꝑſone borne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges obeyſaunce by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure of this acte ſhall haue auctoryte to bye any ledder i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſecrete place / but oon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in open markettes and Fayres.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ꝑſone by coloure of this Acte haue auctoryte to bye or ſelle any ledder within the Cytie of London / but if eyther the bier or the ſeller be a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man af the ſayd Cytie accordynge to the auncyent cuſtomes &amp; liberties of the ſayd Cytie and accordynge to dyuerſe eſtatutes in that caſe made and puruayed except oonly in ſeynt Bartylmewes fayre.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alſo that this Acte ſhall not extende to take awaye or mynyſſhe any powre or auctoryte gyuen by the ſayd former eſtatute vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wardens of the fely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe of Coryours and to theyr ſucceſſours for dewe ſerche by them and theyr de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puties to be made in any place or vpon any parſone for ledder vnſuffyciently dreſt / wrought tanned or vnſealed nor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execution of ſuche penalties as be conteyned in the ſayd former acte and ſtatute for the punyſſhementꝭ of ſuche defautes as ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be by the ſayd ſerche founden.</p>
               <p>¶ Prouyded alſo that no parſone borne out of the kynges obeyſaunce haue none auctoryte by reaſon of this acte to begynne any newe markettꝭ within ſeynt Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tens the graunte of London or in any other. Fraunchyſed place / but only ſhall bye in ſuche markettes as haue bene of olde tyme accuſtomed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25461:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>An acte concernynge the maner and fourme of Sute for the kyngꝭ moſt gracyous Letters of generall pardon.</head>
               <head type="sub">Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here hit hath pleaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges hyghnes of his mere mocyon &amp; moſt habundant grace to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to euery of his Subgectes his generall pardon / by his letters patentes to be opteyned of vpon and concernyng all and ſynguler Artycles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned &amp; ſpecyfied in a bylle ſygned with his moſte gracyous hande delyuered and remaynynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cuſtody of his Chaunceller of Englande for the warraunt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Be hit enacted by our ſayde Souerayne lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes
<abbr>eſpirituell</abbr> &amp; <abbr>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall</abbr> / &amp; the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſent Parly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ament aſſembled / and by thauctoryte of the ſame that all &amp; as many / and euery of the kynges Subiectes the whiche at any tyme hereafter wyll Sue for any of the ſayd Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall haue the auantage auayle &amp; benefyte of the ſame Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all and euery of the kynges Courtes to hym or them to be alowed without writte or writtes of allowaunce therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made or Sued / the ſame parſon or parſons payinge oonly ſuche fees aſwell of ſealynge / as other duyties in the kynges Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cery
/ And all other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges Courtes as ſhalbe orderyd aſſygned lymytted and appoynted by our ſayd Souerayne lorde or by ſuche of hys moſte honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyle / as his hyghnes Shal therunto name / And no more neyther Other fees to be Payede for the premyſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis Anno Quinto.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>¶ Here foloweth the Table of Anno Quinto.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Tabula</head>
               <item>¶ Firſte an Acte concernynge Minyſtracyon of Iuſtyce to the kynges ſubiectes of his Cytie of Turney .Capitulo. Primo.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte for trewe makynge of clothes in deuon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called whyte ſtraytes .Ca .ii.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte concernynge whyte wollen clothes of .v. markes and vnder may be ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed ouer the ſees vnſhorne .Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iii.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte for auoydynge diſceytes in worſtedys .Ca
.iiii.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte concernynge Iuries in london .Ca. v.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte concernynge Surgeons to be diſcharged of queſtes &amp; other thynges .Capitulo. vi.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte for Straungers for byinge of lether in open market .Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vii.</item>
               <item>¶ An acte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernynge the maner &amp; fourme of Sute for the kynges moſte gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Letters of generall pardon .Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Explicit Tabula.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25461:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
